I'm a relationship builder.
أنا شخص أبني العلاقات
When you think of a relationship builder,
عندما تفكرون بشخص يبني العلاقات،
don't you just automatically think "architect?"
هل ينصرف ذهنكم تلقائيا إلى "المهندس المعماري؟"
Probably not.
ربما لا.
That's because most people think architects design buildings and cities,
ذلك لأن معظم الناس يعتقدون أن المعماريين يصممون المباني والمدن،
but what we really design are relationships,
لكن نحن حقيقةً نصمم ونبني العلاقات،
because cities are about people.
لأن الناس هم أهم ما في المدن.
They're places where people come together for all kinds of exchange.
يتنقل الناس في عدة أماكن لأسباب متعددة.
And besides, skylines are highly specific urban habitats
بالإضافة أن الأفق تمثل مساكن حضرية مميزة بدرجة كبيرة
with their own insects, plants and animals,
بما تحتويه من حشرات ونباتات وحيوانات،
and even their own weather.
وحتى الطقس الخاص بها.
But today, urban habitats are out of balance.
ولكن اليوم، حدث خلل في توازن المساكن الحضرية.
Climate change, together with political and economic troubles,
تغير المناخ بالإضافة إلى المشاكل السياسية والاقتصادية،
are having an impact;
لها تأثيرها؛
they're adding up and stressing out cities and us,
فهي تغير أحوال المدن والأشخاص،
the people who live in them.
القاطنين فيها.
For me, the field of ecology has provided important insight,
بالنسبة لي فقد قدّم علم البيئة رؤية هامة،
because ecologists don't just look at individual species on their own,
لأن علماء البيئة لا يهتمون بالأنواع المنفردة فحسب،
they look at the relationships between living things
بل يركزون على العلاقات بين جميع الكائنات الحية
and their environment.
وبين البيئة الخاصة بها.
They look at how all the diverse parts of the ecosystem are interconnected,
ويدققون في كيفية ترابط أجزاء النظام البيئي ككل،
and it's actually this balance, this web of life, that sustains life.
وهذا التوازن حقيقةً وشبكة الحياة هما ما يجعل الحياة تستمر.
My team and I have been applying insights from ecology to architecture
وقد قمت أنا وفريقي بتطبيق بعض المفاهيم البيئية على علم العمارة
to see how physical space can help build stronger relationships.
لفهم دور المساحة الطبيعية في بناء علاقات متينة.
The projects I'm going to show you today
ولذلك موضوعي اليوم هو
use the idea of building relationships as the key driver for design.
استخدام فكرة بناء العلاقات كركيزة أساسية للتصميم.
Here's an example of what I mean.
سأعطيكم مثالاً للتوضيح.
Recently, we were asked to design a center for social justice leadership
طُلب منا مؤخرًا تصميم مركزًا لقيادة العدالة الاجتماعية
called the Arcus Center.
يسمى (آركوس سنتر).
They asked us for a building that could break down traditional barriers
طلبوا منا تصميم مبنى يكسر الحواجز التقليدية
between different groups
بين طبقات المجتمع المختلفة
and in doing so, create possibilities for meaningful conversations
وبذلك توجد إمكانيات لإجراء محادثات مفيدة
around social justice.
حول موضوع العدالة الاجتماعية.
The students wanted a place for cultural exchange.
أراد الطلاب مكانًا للتبادل الثقافي.
They thought a place for preparing food together could do that.
واعتقدوا أن إعداد الطعام سويًا في مكان ما قد يفيدهم.
And they wanted to be welcoming to the outside community.
وأرادوا أن يرحب بهم المجتمع الخارجي.
They thought a fireplace could draw people in
اعتقدوا أن مدفأة قد تجذب الناس
and help start conversations.
وتساعدهم في بدء محادثات ما.
And everybody wanted the work of social justice to be visible
أراد الجميع أن يظهر أهمية العدالة الاجتماعية
to the outside world.
للعالم الخارجي.
There really wasn't a precedent for this kind of space,
لم يحدث شيء كهذا من قبل
so we looked around the globe and found examples
لهذا بحثنا حول العالم ووجدنا أمثلة
of community meeting houses.
عن الملتقيات الاجتماعية.
Community meeting houses are places
تُعد الملتقيات الاجتماعية أماكن
where there's very specific relationships between people,
حيث تصنع نوعا من العلاقات الفريدة بين الأفراد،
like this one in Mali, where the elders gather.
مثل ما نرى في دولة مالي، حيث يلتقي كبار السن.
The low roof keeps everybody seated and at equal eye level.
يُبقي السقف المنخفض الحاضرين على الجلوس عند مستوى الرؤية.
It's very egalitarian.
في شكل يعبر عن المساواة.
I mean, you can't stand up and take over the meeting.
أعني أنك لاتستطيع الوقوف و تولّي أمر الاجتماع.
You'd actually bump your head.
حقيقةً سيرتطم رأسك بالسقف.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
In meeting houses, there's always a central space
في مقرات الملتقيات، هناك دائما مساحة مركزية
where you can sit around a circle and see each other.
حيث تجلس في دائرة وترى البقية.
So we designed a space just like that
لذلك صممنا شكلًا مطابقًا
right in the middle of the Arcus Center,
في منتصف (أركوس سنتر)،
and we anchored it with a fireplace and a kitchen.
وثبتناه بواسطة مدفأة ومطبخ.
It's pretty hard to get a kitchen and a fireplace in a building like this
إنه أمر صعب جدا أن تحصل على مدفأة ومطبخ في مكان كهذا
with the building codes,
وفقًا لقوانين المبنى،
but it was so important to the concept, we got it done.
لكنه كان مهمًا لاكتمال الفكرة، لذا تم إنجاز الأمر.
And now the central space works for big social gatherings
والآن تناسب المساحة الدائرية التجمعات الاجتماعية الكبيرة
and a place to meet one-on-one for the very first time.
و مكاناً للقاء الأشخاص مباشرةً للمرة الأولى.
It's almost like this three-way intersection
يشبه غالبا نقطة تلاقي ثلاثية كهذه
that encourages bumping into people and starting a conversation.
تشجع على الإختلاط بالناس والمبادرة بالحديث.
Now you can always pass the kitchen and see something going on.
يمكنك الآن دائماً أن تمرّ بالمطبخ لترى شيئًا يحدث.
You can sit by the fireplace and share stories.
يمكنك الجلوس قرب المدفأة ومشاركة قصصك.
You can study together in big groups or in small ones,
يمكنك الدراسة سويّا في مجموعات صغيرة أو كبيرة،
because the architecture sets up these opportunities.
لأن الهندسة المعمارية توفر هذه الإمكانيات.
Even the construction is about building relationships.
حتى التنفيذ الهندسي هو عبارة عن بناء علاقات.
It's made of cordwood masonry,
هو عبارة عن بناء حجري مطعَّم بالخشب،
which is using logs the way you would use bricks.
التي تستخدم دوائر الخشب بنفس طريقة بناء الطوب.
It's super low-tech and easy to do and anyone can do it --
لا تحتاج إلى الكثير من التكنولوجيا ويستطيع أي شخص القيام بها--
and that's the entire point.
و هذه هي الفكرة بكاملها.
The act of making is a social activity.
عملية الصّنع هي نشاط إجتماعي.
And it's good for the planet, too:
ومفيدة للكوكب أيضًا:
the trees absorbed carbon when they were growing up,
امتصّت الأشجار الكربون خلال فترة النمو،
and they gave off oxygen,
و أخرجت الأوكسجين،
and now that carbon is trapped inside the walls
و الآن الكربون عالق داخل الجدران
and it's not being released into the atmosphere.
و لم يُطرَح إلى الجو.
So making the walls is equivalent to taking cars right off the road.
لذلك صنع الجدران يُعد مماثلا لإخلاء الطرق من السيّارات.
We chose the building method
اخترنا طريقة البناء
because it connects people to each other and to the environment.
لأنها تقرّب النّاس إلى بعضهم البعض و إلى البيئة.
But is it working?
لكن هل هي فعّالة؟
Is it creating relationships and nurturing them?
هل تقوم على إيجاد العلاقات و تعزيزها؟
How can we know?
كيف يمكننا أن نعرف؟
Well, more and more people are coming here, for one,
حسناً، يأتي الكثير من الناس هنا،
and as a result of the fireside chats
و كنتيجة للحديث قرب المدفأة
and a full calendar of programming,
ونظام تقويم كامل من البرمجة،
people are applying for the Arcus Fellowships.
يتقدم الناس لـ(زمالة آركوس).
In fact, applications have increased tenfold for the Arcus Fellowship
في الحقيقة، زادت الطلبات لهذه الزمالة عشرة أضعاف
since the building opened.
منذ أن افتُتِح البناء.
It's working. It's bringing people together.
إنّها فعّالة، تجمع النّاس ببعضهم.
So I've shown how architecture can connect people
لقد أظهرت قدرة الهندسة المعماريّة على جمع الناس
on this kind of horizontal campus scale.
على هذا المستوى الأفقي من الحرم الجامعي.
But we wondered if social relationships could be scaled up --
لكنّنا تساءلنا إذا أمكن مدّ العلاقات الإجتماعية إلى الأعلى --
or rather, upward -- in tall buildings.
أو بالأحرى إلى فوق-- في الأبنية العالية.
Tall buildings don't necessarily lend themselves to being social buildings.
هذه الأبنية ليست بالضرورة ذات صبغة اجتماعية.
They can seem isolating and inward.
يمكن أن تبدو عازلة و منغلقة.
You might only see people in those awkward elevator rides.
قد ترى الناس فقط في جولات المصعد المربكة.
But in several major cities, I've been designing tall buildings
و لكن في مدن كبيرة عديدة، كنت أصمم مباني عالية
that are based on creating relationships between people.
ترتكز على إيجاد علاقات بين الناس.
This is Aqua.
هذا مبنى (الأكوا).
It's a residential high-rise in Chicago
بناء سكني عالي في شيكاغو
aimed at young urban professionals and empty nesters,
يستهدف المهنيين المرموقين والأهل الذين يعيشون بمفردهم،
many of them new to the city.
العديد منهم جدد في المدينة.
With over 700 apartments, we wanted to see if we could use architecture
في أكثر من ٧٠٠ شقّة أردنا معرفة إن كان بإمكاننا استخدام هندسة العمارة
to help people get to know their neighbors,
لمساعدة الناس في التعرّف على جيرانهم،
even when their homes are organized in the vertical dimension.
حتى وإن كانت منازلهم مصمَّمة بالبُعْد الرأسي.
So we invented a way to use balconies as the new social connectors.
لذلك اخترعنا وسيلة لاستخدام الشّرفة لغرض التواصل الإجتماعي.
The shapes of the floor slabs vary slightly and they transition
أشكال كل طابق تتنوّع و تختلف
as you go up the tower.
كلّما صعدت لأعلى البناء.
The result of this is that you can actually see people
نتيجة هذا أنّه يمكنك حقيقةً رؤية النّاس
from your balcony.
من شرفتك.
The balconies are misregistered.
الشرفات غيرمتّصلة.
You can lean over your balcony and say, "Hey!"
يمكنك الإطلال من شرفتك وتقول "مرحبًا!"
just like you would across the backyard.
كلما عبرت الساحة الخلفية.
To make the balconies more comfortable
لجعل الشرف مريحة أكثر
for a longer period of time during the year,
لفترة أطول من الوقت خلال السنة،
we studied the wind with digital simulations,
درسنا حركة الرياح باستخدام محاكاة رقْمية،
so the effect of the balcony shapes breaks up the wind
حيث أنّ تأثير أشكال الشُّرفة يخفّف من حدّة الريح
and confuses the wind
و يربك الرياح
and makes the balconies more comfortable and less windy.
ويجعل الشّرفات مريحة أكثر وأقل عصفًا.
Now, just by being able to go outside on your balcony
الآن، القدرة على الخروج إلى شرفتك
or on the third floor roof terrace,
أو إلى سطيحة الطابق الثالث،
you can be connected to the outdoors,
يمكنك التواصل مع من بالخارج،
even when you're way above the ground plane.
حتّى لو كنت بعيدا عن مستوى الأرض.
So the building acts to create community
إذن يؤثر المبنى في خلق مجتمعًا
within the building and the city at the same time.
داخل المبنى والمدينة في آن واحد.
It's working.
إنّها فعّالة.
And people are starting to meet each other on the building surface
ويبدأ الناس بلقاء بعضهم على سطح المبنى
and we've heard --
و طرأ إلى مسامعنا --
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
they've even starting getting together as couples.
أنّهم حتّى بدؤوا يلتقون كثنائي.
But besides romantic relationships,
لكن إلى جانب العلاقات الرومانسية،
the building has a positive social effect
يترك المبنى تأثيرًا اجتماعيًا إيجابيًا
on the community,
على المجتمع،
as evidenced by people starting groups together
بدليل أنّ الناس بدأت بتكوين مجموعات معًا
and starting big projects together,
و بدأت بمشاريع كبيرة سويّا،
like this organic community garden on the building's roof terrace.
مثل حديقة عضوية مجتمعية على شرفة سطح المبنى.
So I've shown how tall buildings can be social connectors,
لذا أظهرتُ كيف يمكن للأبنية العالية أن تمثل روابط إجتماعية،
but what about public architecture?
لكن ماذا عن الهندسة المعمارية العامّة؟
How can we create better social cohesion in public buildings
كيف يمكننا أن نخلق ترابط اجتماعي أفضل في الأبنية العامّة
and civic spaces,
و مساحات للمواطنين،
and why is it important?
و لماذا تعد ضروريّة؟
Public architecture is just not as successful
معمار الأبنية العامّة ليس ناجحًا بهذا القدر
if it comes from the top down.
إذا كان من أعلى لأسفل.
About 15 years ago in Chicago,
منذ نحو ١٥ سنة في شيكاغو،
they started to replace old police stations,
بدأوا باستبدال مراكز الشّرطة القديمة،
and they built this identical model all over the city.
و بنوا هذا النموذج المتطابق في كل أرجاء المدينة.
And even though they had good intentions
بالرّغم من نيتهم الحسنة
of treating all neighborhoods equally,
في معاملة جميع الجيران بتساوٍ،
the communities didn't feel invested in the process
لم تشعر المجتمعات أنها معنيّة
or feel a sense of ownership of these buildings.
أو لم تشعر بامتلاك هذه الأبنية.
It was equality in the sense that everybody gets the same police station,
كانت المساواة تتمثل في أن الجميع لديه نفس مركز الشرطة،
but it wasn't equity in the sense of responding
لكنّها لم تكن منصفة من ناحية الاستجابة
to each community's individual needs.
إلى احتياجات كل أفراد المجتمع.
And equity is the key issue here.
و المساواة هي الأمر الأساسي هنا.
You know, in my field, there's a debate
كما تعلمون، في مجالي، هناك مناظرة
about whether architecture can even do anything
حول إن كانت هندسة العمارة قادرة على فعل أي شيء
to improve social relationships.
لتحسين العلاقات الإجتماعيّة.
But I believe that we need architecture and every tool in our tool kit
لكن أعتقد أنّنا بحاجة إلى فنّ العمارة، وإلى كل أداة في عدّة الأدوات
to improve these relationships.
لتحسين هذه العلاقات.
In the US, policy reforms have been recommended
في الولايات المتّحدة، اقتُرِح عمل إصلاحات في السياسات
in order to rebuild trust.
من أجل إعادة بناء الثّقة.
But my team and I wondered
لكني و فريقي تساءلنا
if design and a more inclusive design process
إن كان التصميم ونهجه أكثر شموليّة
could help add something positive to this policy conversation.
يمكنه المساعدة في إضفاء إيجابية على المحادثات بشأن السياسات.
We asked ourselves simply:
سألنا أنفسنا ببساطة:
Can design help rebuild trust?
هل يساعد التصميم في إعادة بناء الثّقة؟
So we reached out to community members and police officers in North Lawndale;
لذلك، توصلنا إلى أفراد من المجتمع و ضباط شرطة في (شمال لاوندايل):
it's a neighborhood in Chicago
إنه حي مجاور في شيكاغو
where the police station is perceived as a scary fortress
حيث يُعتبر مركز الشّرطة حصنًا مخيفًا
surrounded by a parking lot.
محاط بباحة لوقوف السيّارات.
In North Lawndale, people are afraid of police
في شمال لاونديل، يخاف النّاس من الشّرطة
and of going anywhere near the police station,
أو من الذّهاب إلى أي مكان يجاور مركز الشرطة،
even to report a crime.
حتّى للإبلاغ عن جريمة.
So we organized this brainstorming session
لذلك نظمنا هذه الجلسة لإيجاد الأفكار
with both groups participating,
حيث يشارك فيها مجموعتان،
and we came up with this whole new idea for the police station.
و لقد خلُصنا إلى فكرة جديدة برمتها من أجل مركز الشّرطة.
It's called "Polis Station."
اسمها "بوليس ستايشن."
"Polis" is a Greek word that means a place with a sense of community.
"بوليس" هي كلمة يونانيّة تعني مكان فيه دلالة على التجمع.
It's based on the idea
إنّها قائمة على فكرة أن
that if you can increase opportunities for positive social interactions
إذا كان بإمكانك زيادة الفرص من أجل تفاعل إجتماعي إيجابي
between police and community members,
بين الشّرطة وأفراد المجتمع،
you can rebuild that relationship
يمكنك بناء هذه العلاقة
and activate the neighborhood at the same time.
و تنشيط الحيّ في آنٍ واحد.
Instead of the police station as a scary fortress,
بدلاً من الخلفية المخيفة عن مركز الشرطة،
you get highly active spaces on the public side of the station --
تحصل على أماكن مفعمة بالنشاط في الجانب العام من المركز --
places that spark conversation,
أماكن تحفّز على بدء محادثة،
like a barbershop, a coffee shop
كمحل الحلاقة أو مقهى
or sports courts as well.
أو ملاعب رياضية أيضاً.
Both cops and kids said they love sports.
يحبّ كلا من الشّرطة والأولاد الرّياضة.
These insights came directly from the community members
أتت هذه الآراء مباشرةً من أفراد المجتمع
and the police officers themselves,
وضباط الشرطة أنفسهم،
and as designers, our role was just to connect the dots
و بصفتنا نعمل بالتصميم، اقتصر دورنا فقط على وصل النّقاط
and suggest the first step.
و اقتراح اتخاذ الخطوة الأولى.
So with the help of the city and the parks,
بمساعدة المدينة والمتنزّهات،
we were able to raise funds and design and build a half-court,
استطعنا جمع الأموال وتصميم وبناء نصف ملعب،
right on the police station parking lot.
بجانب موقف سيّارات مركز الشّرطة.
It's a start.
إنّها البداية.
But is it rebuilding trust?
لكن، هل تعيد بناء الثّقة؟
The people in North Lawndale say the kids are using the courts every day
يقول النّاس في شمال لاونديل أنّ الأولاد يستخدمون الملاعب كل يوم
and they even organize tournaments like this one shown here,
حتّى أنّهم بدأوا بتنظيم بطولات، مثل هذه الظاهرة هنا،
and once in a while an officer joins in.
و بين الحين و الأخر ينضم إليهم أحد أفراد الشّرطة.
But now, they even have basketballs inside the station
لكن الآن، لديهم كرات السلّة داخل المركز
that kids can borrow.
ويستطيع الأولاد استعارتها.
And recently they've asked us to expand the courts
و حاليّا طلبوا منا إن كان بإمكاننا توسيع الملاعب
and build a park on the site.
و بناء متنزّه عند الموقع.
And parents report something astonishing.
وبدأ الأهل بالتبليغ عن أشياء مذهلة.
Before, there was fear of going anywhere the station, and now they say
في السابق كان هناك خوف من الذّهاب إلى أي مكان قرب المركز أمّا الآن يقولون
there's a sense that the court is safer than other courts nearby,
أنّهم يشعرون بأن الملعب آمن عن أي ملعب آخر بالجوار،
and they prefer their kids to play here.
و أنهم يفضّلون لأبنائهم اللعب هنا.
So maybe in the future,
فمن المحتمل في المستقبل،
on the public side of the station,
في الجانب العام من المركز،
you might be able to drop in for a haircut at the barbershop
أن تأتي لقص شعرك عند الحلّاق
or reserve the community room for a birthday party
أو تحجز القاعة المجتمعية لحفلة عيد ميلاد
or renew your driver's license
أو تجدّد رخصة القيادة
or get money out of an ATM.
أو تحصل على المال من الصرّاف الآلي.
It can be a place for neighbors to meet each other
يمكن لهذا أن يكون مكانًا للجيران للقاء بعضهم البعض
and to get to know the officers, and vice versa.
و ليتعرّفوا على ضباط الشرطة والعكس.
This is not a utopian fantasy.
إنها ليست خيالا مثاليّا.
It's about how do you design to rebuild trust,
إنّما كيف تصمّم و تعيد بناء الثّقة
trusting relationships?
العلاقات المبنيّة على ثقة
You know, every city has parks, libraries, schools
كما تعلمون، كل مدينة فيها منتزهات ومكتبات ومدارس
and other public buildings
ومباني عامّة أخرى
that have the potential to be reimagined as social connectors.
لديها إمكانية أن يُعاد تخيّلها كوسيلة للترابط إجتماعي،
But reimagining the buildings for the future is going to require
لكن تخيّل أبنية المستقبل سوف يتطلب
engaging the people who live there.
دمج النّاس الذين يعيشون هناك.
Engaging the public can be intimidating, and I've felt that, too.
دمج العامّة قد يكون مخيفًا و شعرت بهذا الشّيء أيضا.
But maybe that's because in architecture school,
لكن ربما لأن في كليّة العمارة،
we don't really learn how to engage the public in the act of design.
لا نتعلّم في الحقيقة كيف يمكن جمع شمل االنّاس في فن التّصميم.
We're taught to defend our design against criticism.
لقد تعلّمنا أن ندافع عن تصميمنا إزاء النقد.
But I think that can change, too.
لكن يمكن لهذا المفهوم أن يتغيّر أيضًا.
So if we can focus the design mind
لذلك إذا ركّزنا في جوهر التصميم
on creating positive, reinforcing relationships
لإيجاد علاقات إيجابية وقوية
in architecture and through architecture,
في الهندسة المعمارية ومن خلالها،
I believe we can do much more than create individual buildings.
أعتقد أننا نستطيع فعل أكثر من إنشاء أبنية منفردة.
We can reduce the stress and the polarization
يمكننا أن نخفّف الضّغط والاستقطاب
in our urban habitats.
في مساكننا الحضرية.
We can create relationships.
يمكننا أن ننشئ علاقات.
We can help steady this planet we all share.
يمكننا أن نساعد في استقرار الكوكب الذي نتشاركه جميعًا.
See?
هل رأيتم؟
Architects really are relationship builders.
مهندسو العمارة بالفعل بنّاؤو علاقات.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Thank you very much.
شكراً جزيلاً
(Applause)
(تصفيق)